Finding Aid for Jacob Ellsworth Reighard Papers 1887-1942
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Correspondence
  - 1910-1919
    - December 1918 (Box 8)
    - January 1919 (Box 8)
    - February 1919 (Box 8)
    - March 1-14, 1919 (Box 8)
    - March 15-31, 1919 (Box 8)
    - April 1919 (Box 8)
    - May 1919 (Box 8)
    - June 1919 (Box 8)
    - July 1919 (Box 8)
    - August 1919 (Box 8)
    - September 1919 (Box 8)
    - October 1919 (Box 8)
    - November 1919 (Box 8)
    - December 1919 (Box 8)
  - 1920-1940
    - January-February 1920 (Box 8)
    - March 1920 (Box 8)
    - April 1920 (Box 8)
    - May 1920 (Box 8)
    - June 1920 (Box 8)
    - July-September 1920 (Box 8)
    - October 1920 (Box 8)
    - November 1920 (Box 8)
    - December 1920 (Box 8)
    - 1921 (Box 8)
    - 1922-1924 (Box 8)
    - 1925 (Box 8)
    - 1926-1927 (Box 8)
    - 1928-1930 (Box 8)
    - 1931-1940 (Box 8)
  - Subject
    - Correspondence, concerning publication of revised edition of Anatomy of the Cat August 1931-March 1932 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, concerning publication of revised edition of Anatomy of the Cat April-December 1932 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, concerning publication of revised edition of Anatomy of the Cat 1933-1935 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, concerning his interest in speech reading and speech correction work 1928-1938 (Box 8)
    - Notes and other materials concerning speech reading (Box 8)
    - "Journal of trip down the Manistee River with W.P. Lombard" August 26-September 14, 1909 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, concerning his resignation from Zoology Department 1922-1927 (Box 8)
- Writings And Speeches
  The Writings and Speeches series (boxes 8-9), though largely concerning fish zoology, also contain lectures on such interesting topics as "Death" (Ann Arbor Unity Club, 1889), Evolution and Darwinism (various talks, 1908-1912), and speech-reading (1926-1927).
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Article, undated: "The Habits of Some American Freshwater Fishes" (Box 8)
  - Lecture material, undated: "The Evolution of the Nest-Building Instinct of Fishes" (Box 8)
  - Article, undated: "Apparatus for Photographing Vertebrate Embryos" (Box 8)
  - Paper, undated: "On the Possibility of Determining the Quantity of Oxygen set free by Aquatic Plants" (Box 8)
  - Paper, undated: "The Fish Hospitals at Loggerhead Key" (Box 8)
  - Article, undated: "Bermudas Fish Problems" (Box 8)
  - Article, undated: "The Breeding Behavior of Nocomis Micropogon (Cope)" (Box 8)
  - Paper, undated: "Sex Recognition and Sexual Selection in Vertebrates" (Box 8)
  - Paper, undated: "A Substitute for the Theory of Warning Coloration" (Box 8)
  - Paper, undated: "The Biological Meaning of Conspicuousness in Animals" (Box 8)
  - Paper, undated: "Warning Colors in Coral Reef Fishes" (Box 8)
    (International Zoological Society, Boston)
  - Paper November 4, 1889 "Death" (Box 8)
    (Ann Arbor Unity Club)
  - Talk 1891 "The Relation of Field Work to the Teaching of the Natural Sciences?" (Box 8)
    (Michigan Schoolmasters Club)
  - Lecture 1892-1893 "Inland Aquarium and Scientific Stations" (Box 8)
    (Prismatic and Bohemian Clubs, Detroit)
  - Talk 1893 Concerning Wall-Eyed Pike (Box 8)
  - Paper March 6, 1893 "Heredity" (Box 8)
  - Talk March 15, 1893 Concerning the Great Lakes (Box 8)
    (Bohemian Club, Detroit)
  - Lecture 1894 "The Work of the State Fish Commission" (Box 8)
  - Paper 1897 "Some characteristics of Recent Work on the Biology of Fresh Waters" (Box 8)
  - Article 1898 "Methods of Plankton Investigation in their Relation to Practical Problems" (Box 8)
  - Lecture 1898 "The Biology of the Great Lakes" (Box 8)
    (Field Museum, Chicago)
  - Speech material, 1899: Concerning Trichina (Box 8)
  - Article 1899 "A Plan for the Investigation of the Biology of the Great Lakes" (Box 8)
  - Talk May 1900 Concerning the Teaching of Biology (Box 8)
    (Appointment Committee Course)
  - Talk 1906 Concerning Human and Animal Behavior (Box 8)
    (University of Kansas; University of Nebraska)
  - Lecture 1907 Concerning Evolution, 4 folders (Box 8)
    (Detroit)
  - Paper, "Evolution of the Pearl Organs of American (Box 9)
  - Minnows and Suckers 1908 (Box 9)
    (Boston)
  - Talk, Concerning Evolution January 18, 1908 (Box 9)
    (Education Club, Detroit)
  - Article, "An Experimental Study of Warning Coloration in Coral Reef Fishes" 1909 (Box 9)
  - Talk, "The Present Status of Darwinism" February 17, 1909 (Box 9)
    (Ann Arbor Research Club)
  - Talk, "Darwinism to Date" February 25, 1909 (Box 9)
    (Twentieth Century Club, Detroit)
  - Article, "The Pearl Organs of American Minnows in their Relation to the Factors of Descent" 1910 (Box 9)
    (Science Magazine)
  - Lecture, "A Naturalist's View of Adaptation" July 14, 1910 (Box 9)
    (popular talk on evolution)
  - Talk, Concerning Evolution 1911 (Box 9)
    (St. Andrew's Episcopal Church, Ann Arbor)
  - Talk, "Birds and Animals of the Woods" March 13, 1911 (Box 9)
    (Boy Scouts talk)
  - Lecture, Concerning Evolution January 12, 1912 (Box 9)
    (Battle Creek, Michigan)
  - Lecture, Symposium on Adaptation April 2, 1914 (Box 9)
    (Michigan Schoolmasters Club, Ann Arbor)
  - Address, "The Senses and Learning in Fishes" October 18, 1916 (Box 9)
    (Presidential Address,American Fisheries Society, New Orleans)
  - Lecture, "Senses and Learning in Fishes" August 15, 1919 (Box 9)
    (Summer Session Lecture)
  - Paper, "The Problems of the Adult Deafened" Scientific Club of the University of Michigan 1924 (Box 9)
  - Article, "The University Teaching of Speechreading to the Adult Deafened" January 19, 1924 (Box 9)
    (School and Society)
  - Paper, "A Preliminary Biological Examination of Loon Lake and Loon Lake Bog Pond on the Sylvania Club Property Gogebic County, Michigan in August 1926" (Box 9)
  - Article, "Speech Reading for the Deafened" July 17, 1926 (Box 9)
  - Talk, Concerning Respiration and Voice 1927 (Box 9)
    (class at Michigan State Normal College)
  - Paper, "Speech-Reading for Adult Deafened May 19, 1927 (Box 9)
    (Zoology Journal Club)
  - Paper, Concerning lip reading November 12, 1927 (Box 9)
    (Scientific Club of the University of Michigan)
  - Talk, "Early Fisheries Work in Michigan" May 29, 1940 (Box 9)
    (Karl Lagler's class)
  - Miscellaneous reprints of writings (Box 9)
- University Lecture And Course Materials
  The University Lecture and Course Materials series (box 9-11) have been arranged either by course or research topic. They contain extensive files for Reighard's courses in Vertebrate Zoology, Organic Evolution, Ecology, and the Literature of Zoology.
  - Biology lecture notes 1887 (Box 9)
  - Zoology 8 and 8a: Vertebrate Zoology and Comparative Anatomy, 24 folders (Box 9)
  - Skate (fish), 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Turtle (Box 9)
  - Wall-Eyed Pike, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Perch, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Teleosto (Box 9)
  - Notes on literature of filling of teleost egg (Box 9)
  - Necturus (Salamander) (Box 9)
  - Organic Evolution, 14 folders (Box 10)
  - Zoology 8 Natural History of Animals with special reference to the principles of ecology and behavior 1916-1917, 10 folders (Box 10)
  - Vertebrate Embryology, 11 folders (Box 10)
  - Zoology 24 Functions and Activities of Animals 1915-1917, 7 folders (Box 10)
  - Zoology 12: Current Literature of Zoology, 8 folders (Box 10)
  - Amblystoma (Salamander) Embryology, 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Pigeons (Box 11)
  - Biology of fresh waters (Box 11)
  - Breeding Habits of Fishes, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Breeding Habits (General), 5 folders (Box 11)
  - General Biology, 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Zoological Journal Club Miscellanea, 4 folders (Box 11)
- Research Materials And Field Notes
  The Research Materials and Field Notes series (boxes 11-13) largely concern observations of Michigan fish. Other topics covered include the establishment of a bureau of fisheries in the Philippine Islands, warning coloration in fish species, and the investigation of possible pollution of the River Raisin near Monroe, Michigan.
  - Campostoma (Stone-Roller Minnow), 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Black Bass (Box 11)
  - Rock Bass (Box 11)
  - Eupomotis Gibbosus (Box 11)
  - Chaenobryttus gulosus (Box 11)
  - Apomotis cyanellus, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Blue Gill (Box 11)
  - Percina caprodes (Box 11)
  - Warning coloration, 10 folders (Box 11)
  - Ichthyomyzon (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 6 folders (Box 11)
  - Underwater photography (Box 11)
  - Zoological laboratory (specifications and descriptions of other laboratories) (Box 11)
  - "Plan for the Establishment of a Bureau of Fisheries and Marine and Freshwater Investigations" (Philippine Islands), 2 folders (Box 11)
  - "An Investigation into the Causes of the Deaths of Carp in the Monroe Carp Pond and in Live Carp in the River Raisin at Monroe, Michigan", 4 volumes (Box 12)
  - River Raisin investigation research files, 32 folders (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous field notes and notebooks (Box 13)
  - Diary, of Paul Roby Reighard 1905 (Box 13)
  - Record book of observations and readings circa 1890 (Box 13)
  - Articles by others (Box 13)
  - "The Distribution of Boleosoma Nigrum in Douglas Lake, Michigan" by Harry V. Heimburger (Box 13)
  - "Report on the Breeding Habits of Sturgeon in the Great Lakes" by S.O. Mast (Box 13)
  - Concerning Yellow-Bellied Sapsucker by Margaret W. Taggart (Box 13)
  - "The Development of the Genital Ducts of Amia Calva" by Waldron (?) (Box 13)
  - "The Lepidoptera of the Douglas Lake Region based on the collections made during the summers of 1911 and 1912" by Paul S. Welch (Box 13)
  - Notes on the development of the Epyphysis by R.H. Wolcott Miscellaneous papers, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Photographs, 10 envelopes (Box 13)
Selective Inventory of Correspondents
Abel, John Jacob (1857-1938)
May 30, 1896
Adams, Charles Christopher, (1873-1955)
Dec. 4, 1902 and earlier; Dec. 23, 1902; Apr. 23, 1903; May 1903, June 1903; July 26, 1903
Agassiz, Alexander (1835-1910)
May 8, 1894; June 22, 1906
Amateur Fencers League of America
Mar. 16, 1915
Angell, James Burrill (1829-1916)
June 28, 1891; Apr. 10,1894; Dec. 2, 1895; Jan. 10, 1896; Feb. 8, 1897, July 2, 1897; Nov. 2, 1898; Aug. 5, 1902; Sept. 5, 1902; Apr. 22, 1903, July 17, 1903; Sept. 10, 1903; June 26, 1906; Sept. 26, 1906
Bailey, Liberty Hyde (1858-1954)
Feb. 15, 1899
Baker, Frank Collins (1867-1942)
May 25, 1906
Barbour, Levi Lewis (1840-1925)
Mar. 2, 1897; Letter to J.C. Burrows, Apr. 22, 1902; June 9, 1902, July,1902; Sept. 23, 1902; Nov. 11, 1902; Jan. 1903; June 1903, Dec. 11, 1903; June 14, 1904
Birge, Edward Asahel (1851-1950)
Feb. 4, 1894; Mar. 1894; May 20, 1894; May 15, 1906; June 7, 1906, Aug. 8, 1906
Bumpus, Hermon Carey (1862-1943)
July 20, 1903
Burrows, Julius Caesar (1837-1915)
Jan. 1902; Jan. 23, 1904; Mar. 14, 1904
Cattell, James McKeen (1860-1944)
Sept. 22, 1903
Clark, Hubert Lyman (1870-1947)
July 31, 1899; Aug. 8, 1899; Mar. 3, 1900; Apr. 1, 1901; Feb. 24, 1902, Mar. 8, 1902; Apr. 22, 1902; May 4, 1905
Clements, William Lawrence (1861-1934)
Feb. 20, 1915
Cobb, Frank Irving (1869-1923)
Feb. 7, 1899; Feb. 12, 1899; Feb. 15, 1899; Feb. 18, 1899
Conklin, Edward Grant (1863-1952)
July 13, 1903
Davenport, Charles Benedict (1866-1944)
Apr. 5, 1900; Dec. 1, 1908
Dean, Bashford (1867-1928)
Nov. 28, 1899; Sept. 4, 1907; Feb. 6, 1909; Feb. 16, 1912; Apr. 6, 1912, Mar. 10, 1915
Dewey, John (1859-1952)
June 6, 1898; Jan. 1902; Mar. 27, 1902; May 1, 1902; Sept. 16, 1902, 1908 undated
Dodge, Charles Wright
Feb. 23, 1915; Feb. 24, 1915
Forbes, Stephen Alfred (1844-1930)
Jan. 1894; Mar. 19, 1894; Sept. 1897; Nov. 17, 1897; May 6, 1898, Jan. 23, 1899; Apr. 30, 1900; June 6, 1901; Feb. 3, 1902; May 9, 1902, June 1902; Nov. 1902; Dec. 3, 1902; Jan. 26, 1903; Oct. 30, 1903, Apr. 12, 1904; June 18, 1904 (copy); July 11, 1905; Apr. 30, 1906, May 26, 1906; June 7, 1909; Feb. 16, 1911; Mar. 4, 1911
Fordney, Joseph Warren (1853-1932)
Jan. 1903; Feb. 12, 1903; Apr. 2, 1903
Gage, Simon Henry (1851-1944)
Oct. 26, 1897; Feb. 1899; Feb. 5, 1903; June 25, 1903; May 1913
Gilman, Daniel Coit (1831-1908)
June 27, 1899
Harvey, Edmund Newton (1887-1959)
Apr. 21, 1919; Apr. 26, 1919
Hay, Oliver Perry (1846-1930)
Apr. 1, 1894
Herrick, Francis Hobart (1858-1940)
Oct. 23, 1901 and earlier; Nov. 2, 1901; May 4, 1903; Apr. 18, 1905, Mar. 26, 1908; May 1911; Jan. 26, 1912; Mar. 27, 1912
Hubbard, Lucius Lee (1849-1933)
Mar. 18, 1910; Mar. 23, 1910 (to W.H. Hobbs); Nov. 1911; Dec. 15, 1911, Jan. 26, 1912
Hubbs,Carl Leavitt (1894-?)
Oct. 20, 1917; Oct. 20, 1919; Nov. 4, 1919
Hutchins, Harry Burns (1847-1930)
Oct. 14, 1915 (to Hutchins re: selection of new Graduate School dean)
Jenks, Jeremiah Whipple (1856-1929)
Feb. 2, 1898
Jennings, Herbert Spencer (1868-1947)
Sept. 28, 1895; Dec. 29, 1895; Feb. 22, 1896 (2); Apr. 1896; May 1, 1896, Jan. 10, 1897; Feb. 28, 1897; Apr. 14, 1897; May 26, 1897; Oct. 30, 1897, Dec. 21, 1897; Jan. 1898; Feb. 22, 1898; Mar. 1898; Apr. 1898; May 1898, June 1898; July 7, 1898; Sept. 1898; Oct. 27, 1898; Nov. 14, 1898, Dec. 25, 1898; Jan. 1899; Feb. 1899; Mar. 1899; Apr. 1899; Apr. 20, 1899, May 1899; June 1899; Sept. 11, 1899; May 1903; June 1903; July 13, 1903, Sept. 4, 1903; Jan. 2, 1904; Aug. 1904; Sept. 29, 1904; Dec. 11, 1904, Mar. 29, 1905; Apr. 8, 1905; Feb. 27, 1906; Sept. 24, 1906; May 1907, July 10, 1907; Apr. 17, 1908; Jan. 23, 1909; Mar. 9, 1909; Apr. 2, 1909, May 30, 1910; Aug. 2, 1910; Feb. 3, 1911; Apr. 16, 1911; May 1911; (also see letters, Aug. 24, 1931; Sept. 19, 1931; Dec. 9, 1931; and Jan. 10, 1933, in folders concerning the publication of the Anatomy of the Cat.)
Johnston, John Black (1868-1939)
July 5, 1901 and earlier; July 16, 1901; Oct. 1901; Nov. 2, 1901, May 21, 1902; June 26, 1902; July 1902; Sept. 21, 1902; Jan. 1903, Mar. 29, 1903; Apr. 22, 1903; Dec. 2, 1903; Jan. 1904; Mar. 22, 1904, Apr. 4, 1904; May 6, 1904; Apr. 16, 1905; Mar. 21, 1906; Mar. 4, 1908, Oct. 20, 1911; Feb. 25, 1912; May 21, 1912; Dec. 1914; Jan. 23, 1915
Jordan,David Starr (1851-1931)
Jan. 9, 1906; Apr. 18, 1911; May 2, 1911
Kellogg, John Harvey (1852-1943)
May 26, 1897; June 9, 1897; June 14, 1897; June 24, 1897
Lane, Alfred Church (1863-1948)
Mar. 13, 1906 and earlier; Apr. 28, 1906; May 1906j June 1906; July 5, 1906; Aug. 1906; Sept. 1, 1906; Nov. 1906; Jan. 24, 1907; Feb. 4, 1907, Apr. 19, 1907; May 18, 1907; July 22, 1909
Langley, Samuel Pierpont (1834-1906)
Jan. 2, 1894
La Rue, George Roger (1882-1967)
Aug. 24, 1914 and earlier; Aug. 28, 1914; Sept. 1914; July 17, 1917, Aug. 10, 1917; July 1918; Aug. 14, 1918; June 12, 1919; July 1919, Aug. 1919; Sept. 20, 1919
Lillie, Frank Rattray (1870-1947)
June 8, 1903 (and earlier); July 24, 1909
Loeb, Jacques (1859-1924)
June 8, 1897; May 1, 1919
McMillan, James (1838-1902)
Letter to J.B. Angell, May 18, 1900; Letter to J.B. Angell, June 12, 1900, Aug. 7, 1901; Dec. 2, 1901; Jan. 1902; Apr. 26, 1902
Mark, Edward Laurens (1847-1946)
Throughout
Meyer, Adolf (1866-1950)
Apr. 8, 1904
Morgan, Thomas Hunt (1866-1945)
Feb. 20, 1893; Mar. 20, 1893
Mosher, Eliza Maria (1846-1928)
Jan. 25, 1903
National Conference on Race Betterment
Dec. 1913 Feb. 1914
Okkelberg, Peter Olaus (1880-?)
Aug. 2, 1914 and earlier
Osborn, Henry Fairfield (1857-1935)
June 14, 1899; Nov. 25, 1908
Peabody, George Foster (1852-1938)
Sept. 26, 1886; Oct. 6, 1906
Pearl, Raymond (1879-1940)
Dec. 3, 1905; Apr. 23, 1906 and throughout earlier; June 1906, July, 4, 1906; Aug. 13, 1906; Sept 7, 1906; Oct. 22, 1906
Oct. 11, .1907, Mar. 17, 1908; Apr. 3, 1908; Sept. 6, 1908; Sept. 26, 1910; May 24, 1913
Pingree, Hazen Smith (1840-1901)
Dec. 29, 1896; Feb. 25, 1899; Mar. 1899
Putnam, Frederic Ward (1839-1915)
Aug. 11, 1903
Ruthven, Alexander Grant (1882-1971)
June 9, 1903; Aug. 12, 1906; July 4, 1907; Sept. 7, 1908; July 24, 1909, July 24, 1910; Sept. 19, 1910; Nov. 23, 1911; Nov. 16, 1915
Jan. 11, 1916, Oct. 5, 1916; Jan. 9, 1917; Mar. 23, 1918; Apr. 2, 1918 (letter concerning pro-German faculty); Apr. 24, 1918 (letter concerning Koelz)
Shull, Aaron Franklin (1881-1961)
July 22, 1909; May 23, 1910 and earlier; Mar. 25, 1911; Sept. 1911, July 14, 1914; Sept. 1918
Smith, William Alden (1859-1932)
Apr. 2, 1912
Stockard, Charles Rupert (1879-1939)
Apr. 28, 1908
Wenley, Robert Mark (1861-1929)
Apr. 25, 1910; Apr. 26, 1910; Apr. 28, 1910
Whitman, Charles Otis (1842-1910)
Oct. 10, 1902 and earlier; Oct. 14, 1902
Woodward, Robert Simpson (1849-1924)
June 23, 1906
Worcester, Dean Conant (1866-1924)
July 31, 1897; Aug. 1897; Sept. 9, 1897; Aug. 30, 1898; Feb. 1899, July 29, 1899; Dec. 6, 1899; Feb. 1900; Apr. 12, 1900; Mar. 9, 1901, May 5, 1901; Jan. 23, 1902
Apr. 23, 1903 (long letter from Phil. Is.) Sept. 3, 1903; Oct. 21, 1903; Mar. 7, 1904; Apr. 19, 1904 (long), Mar. 14, 1907; Apr. 7, 1907; Mar. 26, 1909 (long); July 1909
July 11, 1910; Dec. 12, 1910; Feb. 19, 1914; Apr. 1914; June 29, 1914, Sept. 5, 1914; Dec. 24, 1915